Celebrating Reasonable Doubt's 30th
anniversary by dissecting Jay-Z's most
complex bars from Can't Knock the
Hustle.
>> Chilly with enough bail [music] money to
free a big Willie. High stakes, I got
more at stake than Philly.
>> Jay frames this line with a play on the
famous cartoon Chilly Willy. A big
Willie was 90s slang for a major drug
dealer, while Free Willy was a hit 1993
film about freeing a captive whale. Jay
plays on that premise, boasting he has
enough money to post bail and free a
drug kingpin. But a third layer reveals
itself in the next line. On the surface,
high stakes means Jay has more on the
line, more to lose. But he immediately
flips stake into steak, nodding to
Philadelphia's most famous food, the
cheesesteak. That's clever enough on its
own, but even more impressive when we
realize Big Willie was also the nickname
of rapper and actor Will Smith, who
famously hails from Philadelphia. At the
time, Fresh Prince of Bel-Air was one of
the country's biggest TV shows, where
Will Smith moves into his rich Uncle
Phil's Bel-Air estate. Thus, we realize
Jay could be bending at stake to sound
like estate, while Philly certainly nods
to Uncle Phil, meaning Jay has more
wealth than Uncle Phil himself.